<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>An Answer to a libel entituled, A dialogue between Dr. H.C. [i.e. Hugh Chamberlen] and a country-gentleman</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1696</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 69 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 13 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A25531</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing A3321</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R15857</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">11926447</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 11926447</idno>
            <idno type="VID">51040</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A25531)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 51040)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 48:18)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>An Answer to a libel entituled, A dialogue between Dr. H.C. [i.e. Hugh Chamberlen] and a country-gentleman</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>24 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed and sold by T. Sowle ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1696.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Relates to Dr. Chamberlen's scheme for a land bank.</note>
                  <note>Caption title.</note>
                  <note>Imprint from colophon.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Columbia University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Chamberlen, Hugh. --  Dialogue between Dr. H.C. and a country-gentleman.</term>
               <term>Land banks --  England.</term>
               <term>Banks and banking --  England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-06</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-08</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-08</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:51040:1"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:51040:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>AN ANSWER TO A LIBEL ENTITULED, A DIALOGUE BETWEEN Dr. <hi>H. C.</hi> and a Country-Gentleman.</head>
            <p>HAving lately ſeen ſcatter'd up and down in Cof<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fee-Houſes, an Inſſipid yet Malicious Sheet, intituled, <hi>A Dialogue between Dr.</hi> H. C. <hi>and a Countrey-Gentleman;</hi> and having taken the pains to peruſe it, I found it ſo falſe and ſenſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs a Trifle, as not to deſerve the Regard or Notice of any Underſtanding Man. But be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing informed that the Author's Partiſans hugg'd themſelves up with the Imaginary Victory, gain'd by this Doughty Tool; and becauſe ſome, ignorant of the Nature of the Doctor's Great Deſign, might poſſibly be miſled by this Trifler into wrong Idea's of it; and partly, that this pert Dialogue-Monger may not Triumph in his little Non<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenſe, and think his Scribble unanſwerable, becauſe it was deſpis'd: I
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:51040:2"/>am content for once to rake in his Dunghil, and to ſet That in its True Light, which he hath ſo maliciouſly, yet weakly, endeavour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to Obſcure and Deform.</p>
            <p>The Author deſigned it a Libel, as it appears by the manner of its coming Abroad, having been plentifully diſperſed in Town and Country, without either the Authors or the Printers Name; and the Author has thus far ſucceeded, that he has ſhewn enough of the Malice, tho' none of the Wit, of a Libeller. But as <hi>Jo: Briſcoe</hi> ſays, in his Anſwer to the Uſurer, <hi>Not knowing what Impreſſions the ſame may make on ſuch, who may read it over ſuperficially, but will not ſpare time to examine into his Arguments,</hi> I ſhall with what brevity I can, detect their Fallacy: And ſhall not therefore inſiſt on his ſilly Quibbles and impertinent Tautologies, but firſt take notice of his charging the Doctor falſly, <hi>viz. Dr. How come you to pretend to be the firſt Propoſer of a Bank in</hi> England? <hi>For now you put me in mind on't, you laid claim to the Bank of</hi> England <hi>as yours:</hi> And in the Margent quotes <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſeful Reflections,</hi> &amp;c. page 3. To which place I turned, and there find it thus expreſſed, viz. <hi>But yet notwithſtanding I do for divers Reaſons think any Bank is better here than Money-Banks. But ſuch as are for founding Banks Originally upon a Revenue, or Goods, muſt rob the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctor of the Fruits of his Labour, Charge, and Invention, if they do not conſider him accordingly.</hi>—And all this is writ by a third Perſon.</p>
            <p>Wherein now does it appear that the Doctor challenges this Bank as his, or any part of it? Save that he ſays, he was the firſt Inventor of Banks Originally upon a Revenue or Goods, but altogether con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demns this of Money: And to my certain knowledge, did uſe many Arguments againſt all the Prejudices and Inconveniences, which he fore-ſaw would be the ſure Conſequences of this Bank, and which the People have ſince moſt ſenſibly felt. But our Falſifier a little after proceeds in anſwer to the Doctor's Notion of firſt giving a Credit up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on Land, <hi>viz. Excuſe me, good Doctor, if I differ from you; That Notion was in the World ſome hundred of years before you or they were born, and therefore neither you nor they can pretend to be the Authors of it:</hi> And in the Margent he obſerves <hi>that every Mortgage is a Credit upon Land, and every time a Mortgage is aſſigned, it paſſes in payment for ſo much Money as it is aſſigned for.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Here our Junior Soph has notably contrived to confound the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctor's Notion of iſſuing out Bills of Credit on Land, with that of Mortgages, which is indeed a Credit on Land likewiſe, but much dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferent in the manner: For the Bills of Land-Credit deſigned by the Doctor, are after a more uſeful Method, of dividing a Mortgage in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to ſo many leſſer ſums, and making them payable as Money to any
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:51040:2"/>Man, without the tedious Trouble and Expence of all Parties meet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing together, treating, conſulting, and aſſigning, as is always done in the borrowing Money on a Mortgage; neither can a Man be al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways readily and eaſily ſupplied with the whole Sum due on a Mort<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gage, when he hath an occaſion for that Money again; or will he part with it, unleſs the whole be paid down; which if the Sum be large, may be offered to fifty, before he meets with one, that may an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer his ends: From which follows this deſtructive conſequence to ſo many Mortgagers, that oftentimes for want of paying or procu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring part of the Principal or Intereſt, they are proſecuted for the whole; whereas if their Lands were mortgaged to Truſtees of a Bank, and Bills of Credit given out thereupon, thoſe Bills would in all reſpects be as ſerviceable a Money in ſpecie, and no Man could then be ever ſo ſtreightned as before: And this is that ſort of Credit upon Land, which the Doctor pretends to be the firſt Inventor of, and which was ſo well approved of by two Committees of Parliament, that one of them had agreed to Report it, but the other actually did Report it Profitable and Practicable; the latter Report having been actually made to the Houſe, is to be ſeen in the Printed Votes of the fifth of <hi>February,</hi> 1693. but the firſt Report, tho' agreed by the Committee, was not made to the Houſe, being hindred by a too ſpeed dy Riſing of that Seſſion, yet can be made out by divers worthy Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers, beyond the Contradiction of this Defamer, or any of his Adhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents.</p>
            <p>The next thing obſervable is, where he makes the Doctor ſay, <hi>And I propoſe to iſſue out Tickets to</hi> 10000 l. <hi>value, upon the aforeſaid Security; there's a Notion for you.</hi> Gent. anſwers, <hi>A Notion indeed, Doctor; but what Security, I pray, have thoſe who are to receive your Tickets in pay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment? for if your Fund be bad, your Tickets will not be current; and</hi> 150 l. <hi>a year is not a Security for</hi> 10000 l. In the Margent is <hi>ibid, id eſt, Bank-Dialogue,</hi> page 3. which I have read over, and cannot find the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctor ſays any ſuch thing there, tho' he does ſo elſewhere; but it is thus expreſt: <hi>I never yet heard it was a Crime for any Perſon to lend</hi> 10000 <hi>l. upon</hi> 100 <hi>l. a Year Security; nor for any one to borrow ſo much, if he could.</hi> But this Notion is more at large treated of, in the <hi>Rod for the Fools Back;</hi> only the Author did not care to quote it right, leſt the ſame Rod that corrected there, ſhould turn upon this Kn—as well as that Fool. Since our Caviller will not comprehend this Notion aright, therefore he would not have any body elſe underſtand it, bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter than himſelf would ſeem to do; the Security he queſtions to thoſe who are to receive the Tickets, is not fairly ſtated by him; for he goes on this Suppoſition, If the Fund be bad, your Tickets will not be cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent;
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:51040:3"/>true, but then <hi>vice verſa,</hi> if the Fund be good, the Tickets will be Current, according to his own way of reaſoning. But that the Fund is bad, hardly any rational man, eſpecially converſant in Trade or Buſineſs will, if unbyaſſed, admit; unleſs it be ſuppoſed that no Land in <hi>England</hi> hath any good Title to it, ſince the Fund propoſed, is the Eſtates of Landed Gentlemen in <hi>England;</hi> and tho' one or two prove bad, it does not follow, that all muſt be ſo; and it's much if the badneſs of the Title be not diſcovered upon ſo ſtrickt an enquiry as will be made; ſo that, if any other can ſhew a better Title, the preſent Subſcriber ſhall not be admitted, and if the fraud be diſcovered before four Years are expired, then there will pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently be a ſtop put to the Bills on that Eſtate; but ſuppoſe that ſome few Titles prove bad, yet there will be enough beſides to make all good, there being an allowance for bad Titles, as Merchants al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low for Ware and Tare, Loſſes at Sea, and Bad Debts. So that I hope here is enough ſaid for the badneſs of the Fund, in reſpect to its Title: Then it remains only to ſpeak to its badneſs, in reſpect of its inſufficiency; <hi>viz.</hi> that 150 <hi>l.</hi> a Year is not a Security for 10000 <hi>l.</hi> and he makes the Doctor to anſwer, <hi>I don't ſay it is ſo, do I?</hi> and quotes the <hi>Rod for the Fools Back,</hi> page <hi>6th.</hi> in which Page, I find it thus expreſt. <hi>For neither the Doctor, nor the Author do any where affirm, that</hi> 2000 l. <hi>Fund or Value in Land is a Security for</hi> 10000 l. <hi>as you ſay they do, to ſell at the Market-Price as it now goes.</hi> This was ſaid in Anſwer to a Scurrilous Pamphlet againſt the Doctor put forth by one <hi>Blake</hi> a Scrivener (as 'tis reported he bragg'd) by advice of <hi>Jo. Briſcoe,</hi> and a little after, the Doctor's Propoſal it ſelf is ſet down, which ſays, <hi>That</hi> 150 l. <hi>a Year, together with the</hi> 2000 l. <hi>Stock in Trade, is a ſufficient Security for the Payment of a Rent of</hi> 100 l. <hi>a Year to the Office, which does not amount to that great Sum of</hi> 10000 l. <hi>till</hi> 100 <hi>Years are expired.</hi> And a little lower it follows thus, <hi>That the</hi> 10000 l. <hi>is not to be borrowed at Intereſt of any Private Perſon, or Publick Society; but to be made out of the Mint, and Lent to the Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribers, and other uſes aforeſaid, and to be repaid, but not all at once, with Intereſt, as in the Caſe of all other common Mortgages, where the Creditor can call in both Principal and Intereſt when he pleaſes; but to be a hundred Years in paying, at</hi> 100 l. <hi>a Year only, which in the end makes up</hi> 10000 l. <hi>and thus the</hi> 150 l. <hi>a Year, and Stock, may be Security enough.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>When this Book was Printed, it was hoped and endeavoured by Dr. <hi>Chamberlen</hi> to prevail with the Parliament to make the Tickets, for want of Money, to paſs by an Act, as ready Money in all pay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments; ſo that then there would not have been any need of a Summ
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:51040:3"/>
               <hi>in ſpecie</hi> in the Office to circulate them, and therefore the ſaid Secu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity was in all reſpects very ſufficient to anſwer 10000 <hi>l.</hi> in ſuch a length of time, as the Doctor propoſed it ſhould be repaid, though not all preſently, as if the Eſtates were to be ſold at the preſent Market Price.</p>
            <p>And whereas he makes the Doctor ſpeak thus, <hi>viz. I ſay they will have</hi> 22500 l. <hi>Security for every</hi> 10000 l. <hi>Tickets that will be delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red out;</hi> which hath occaſion'd one whole Column of Scribble in the ſaid Dialogue; In Anſwer, it is neceſſary to let you know, that Mr. <hi>Impudence,</hi> the then Objector, did then, as our preſent Dialogue-mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger does now, make no difference between a Fund of Land, ſettled for the payment of 10000 <hi>l.</hi> preſently, as they underſtand it, and 10000 <hi>l.</hi> to be an hundred years in paying, it being in no ſort equal, or the ſame thing, or of the ſame value, as they fallaciouſly repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent it; and therefore it is thus expreſs'd in the <hi>Rod for Fools Back,</hi> Page 10th. <hi>I would ask both</hi> Blockhead, <hi>and</hi> Briſcoe <hi>this one Queſtion, ſuppoſe they had</hi> 10000 l. <hi>to diſpoſe of, and here are two Offers made them, one of</hi> 500 l. per Annum <hi>to be ſold for ſuch a Summ, and another of</hi> 150 l. <hi>a Year to be Mortgaged for</hi> 150 <hi>Years, the Profits whereof do plainly amount to</hi> 22500, <hi>at the end of the ſaid Term (and as ſo much ready Money according to their Notion is to be valued) which of theſe two Offers will they let go their</hi> 10000 l. <hi>for? No doubt they would think it an hard Bargain, if they were forced to take the</hi> 150 l. per Annum <hi>for their Money, though according to their own way of reckoning it will raiſe</hi> 22500 l. and on this ſcore, and for this Reaſon it was ſo ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſt in the Bank Dialogue.</p>
            <p>But to proceed with the Pamphlet in Hand, <hi>Make out that, Doctor,</hi> (ſays our nameleſs Libeller) <hi>and you do your Work; for I do not find any more than an</hi> 150 l. per Annum <hi>Security for</hi> 10000 l. page 2. I find this <hi>Jack Nubibus</hi> is not ſo very lucky as he thinks himſelf, at Bantering', or at making Objections; or elſe he would have ſaid, That tho' the Office does not, like a common Mort<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gage, oblige the Subſcriber to pay in all his 10000 <hi>l,</hi> preſently, or on half a years notice, yet other People will bring in the Bills, and will expect either to have their Money preſently paid, at ſight of the Bills, or will not take the Bills, becauſe the Security of 150 <hi>l. per an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num,</hi> is not ſufficient to anſwer for them preſently; which I take to be the weightieſt Objection: And yet take it which way you will, it is not truly ſtated; for as the <hi>Doctor</hi> hath now propoſed it, there is 3000 <hi>l.</hi> depoſited in the Joynt Stock, beſides the 150 <hi>l. per annum,</hi> to be Security for the 10000 <hi>l.</hi> and is very ſufficient, according to what <hi>Jo. Briſcoe,</hi> one of the <hi>Doctor's</hi> principal Adverſaries, has affirmed, in
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:51040:4"/>his anſwer to the Uſurers Objection, <hi>viz. But I propoſe a way to the Freeholder, how he may have</hi> 1500 <hi>l. on</hi> 100 <hi>l.</hi> per annum, <hi>for</hi> 3 <hi>l.</hi> per Cent. <hi>being no more than</hi> 45 <hi>l.</hi> per Cent. per Annum, <hi>and that without any further charge; and if he will ſell his Eſtate, after ſuch Reduction of Inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt, he ſhall have</hi> 40 <hi>years Purchaſe for it,</hi> (<hi>for Land will be worth</hi> 40 <hi>years purchaſe, if Intereſt be reduced to</hi> 3 <hi>l.</hi> per Cent.) <hi>I fancy our <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rer will not be able, with all his Rhetorick, to perſwade the Freeholder that this is but an Imaginary, and not a Real Improvement of his Eſtate, and that he is never a whit the richer.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And the Methods, by which he propoſes the Reduction of Inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt, are by Bills of Credit, which he confirms in all his Papers; and particularly in his Queries at the end of the ſaid quoted Print, which he deſires the Uſurer to anſwer. <hi>Query</hi> 2d.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>If there be not Money in Specie ſufficient for our Trade, whether we muſt not make uſe of Credit to ſupply that Defect, or muſt leave Trading?</hi> And a little lower,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>If Credit ſupplying the Defects of Money, abates the Intereſt of Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney, why may not the Freeholders of</hi> England <hi>have a Credit upon their Lands, as well as others upon their bare Notes, without paying</hi> 6 l. per Cent. per Annum <hi>for the ſame?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Then I ſay, Since it is fairly granted, (and indeed warranted by continual Practice) that Bills of Credit can ſupply the want of Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney, and that by giving out Bills of Credit to the value of 15 years Purchaſe on an Eſtate, it will reduce Intereſt of Money to 3 <hi>l. per Cent.</hi> and conſequently advance Land to 40 years Purchaſe; it muſt by the ſame Rule of Reaſon follow, that raiſing above treble the va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lue in Credit on an Eſtate, will lower Intereſt to 2 <hi>l. per Cent.</hi> and ſo advance Land to 60 years Purchaſe; and then 150 <hi>l. per annum</hi> will be worth 9000 <hi>l.</hi> which with the 3000 <hi>l.</hi> in Stock, makes 12000 <hi>l.</hi> which ſure will paſs for a very good Security for 10000 <hi>l.</hi> And at 40 years Purchaſe it will be worth 6000 <hi>l.</hi> which with the 3000 <hi>l.</hi> Stock, makes 9000 <hi>l.</hi> And this comes ſomething near the matter; and 1000 <hi>l.</hi> extraordinary more than what ſuch an Eſtate will yield, may be allow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to be raiſed thereon, as well as to truſt any Man with 100 <hi>l.</hi> or 1000 <hi>l.</hi> on his bare Note only, without other Security; for that the Eſtate in time will certainly pay it off, and in a few years bring it to the fore ſaid Security of 9000 <hi>l.</hi> But the Perſonal Credit is very hazardous, and hath often proved Fatal, as many Gentlemen too well know, by Woful Experience of ſeveral Banking Gold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſmiths.</p>
            <p>But ſuppoſe that every 10000 <hi>l.</hi> had 600 <hi>l. per annum</hi> tyed to make it good, and ſuch a Security, I find, would ſatisfie this Man of Cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure,
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:51040:4"/>and make him, and all ſuch ſcrupulous Objectors, (like him more Nice than Wiſe) allow the Bills to paſs for good; and ſuppoſe too, that they were to be bought all up at 100 <hi>l.</hi> a year; are the Bills the better, for that there is more Land tied to make them good, ſince there will be ſtill the ſame length of time, before they will be all bought up, as the 100 <hi>l.</hi> a year of the 600 <hi>l.</hi> will annually do? And notwithſtanding but 150 <hi>l.</hi> a year is tied, and that the Office does want Moneys to exchange the Bills, muſt the Eſtate be preſently ſold any more the ſooner, than if there were 600 <hi>l.</hi> a year to anſwer 10000 <hi>l.</hi> in which caſe it's poſſible the Office on ſome emergent occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions may equally be under the ſame wants of ready Caſh? No cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly, for the Bills will perform their Office of paying Debts, as well then, as before, when there was Caſh to exchange them; and like a Gentleman's Rents, the next Week or Quarter, more Money comes in, to ſupply that defect; and it's much better to know the utmoſt Credit that will be given out on an Eſtate; and the certain times when it will be diſcharged; than do as the other Banks, that pretend to grant but 15 years Bills of Credit, yet <hi>privately</hi> give out 2 or 300 years Credit, without Notice, Leave or Limitation.</p>
            <p>By all which Premiſes it appears plainly, I think, that the <hi>Doctor</hi>'s propoſed Security can anſwer fully as to length of time, and other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe alſo, according to his Adverſary <hi>Briſcoe</hi>'s Judgment, on the account of raiſing a large Credit thereupon; for that he propoſeth to lend 500 <hi>l.</hi> more than any Scrivener or Uſurer will commonly lend on 100 <hi>l. per annum.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It only remains to ſatisfie the World, That the Bills ſhall be all anſwered with Ready Money, and then this Dialogue is fully anſwer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and its Malice will be of no force: Let it then be conſidered, that tho' 10000 <hi>l.</hi> be raiſed on 150 <hi>l. per annum,</hi> yet not all at once, and not till four years are compleated; there being to be delivered out the firſt year but 1000 <hi>l.</hi> in Bills, to circulate which, beſides other proviſion of Money, 400 <hi>l.</hi> in ſpecie is paid in by the Subſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers, or ſome others for them; a year after, 1100 <hi>l.</hi> in Bills, and 300 <hi>l.</hi> in ſpecie paid in; two years from thence, 1200 <hi>l.</hi> in Bills, and 200 <hi>l.</hi> in ſpecie: So then, the Bills in all, without the Money to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>change them, will be 2400 <hi>l.</hi> And certainly 150 <hi>l. per annum</hi> will be full Security for ſo many Bills, and 900 <hi>l.</hi> in ſpecie, ſufficient to cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culate 2400 <hi>l.</hi> in Bills (which is more than other Banks have ever yet allowed:) In the mean time, the Bills will be ſcattered all about in the Nation; and in all probability, will gain ſuch a Reputation as may make them unqueſtionable for the future; eſpecially when it ſhall be known that many other great moneyed Perſons, as well as the
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:51040:5"/>Subſcribers, have aſſured the <hi>Doctor</hi> and his Managers, That they will depoſit all their Caſh, and order all their Rents and other Payments, to be made and brought into this Office, as now they do in Goldſmiths hands; and take our Bills of Credit, as now their Notes; being ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfied with this conſideration, That tho' it ſhould happen (which is very unlikely) that all the Caſh ſhould be exhauſted at any time, yet the Land is obliged annually to buy them up, ſo that they ſhall not, nor can be Loſers. And ſuppoſing the worſt, yet the Returns of the Joynt Stock in Trade, together with the Rents of the Subſcribers and others, cannot let the Office be long out of Caſh to anſwer the Bills. The third year there will be above 3000 <hi>l.</hi> paid to the Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcriber, but before that time the Joynt Stock will be in motion; and as the Governours of the Stock pay away their Bills for Goods, ſo they will agree to take the Bills again as readily as Money in ſpecie, for all their Goods as they trade in, which will circulate the Bills as well, as if they were changed for ready Money: Beſides, the Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribers agreeing to take them in Rents, and Fines, as well as all other Payments, will encourage their Tenants to receive them; ſo that Men need not trouble themſelves always to go, or ſend to the Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice, to exchange their Bills; becauſe there will be ſo many Perſons ſcatter'd all over the Nation, who will receive or change them as well as the Office. Credit does always beget Credit; or elſe how comes a young Goldſmith, not worth above 500 <hi>l.</hi> in about three or four years, if careful, and exact in his Payments, to be truſted with above 10000 <hi>l.</hi> and give out Bills to 4 or 5000 <hi>l.</hi> at leaſt, tho' never any Goldſmith did ſettle any Land or Fund for all this Money or Credit? And thus he ſhall have a far better Credit than a Gentleman of 2000 <hi>l.</hi> a year in Land: There can be no other Reaſon, than that ſuch Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tlemen mind their pleaſures, and ſpend their Money more profuſely, not caring to be ſo exact in their Times and Payments, but think they may do Buſineſs at their leaſure; neither have they occaſion to deal with ſo many Men of Buſineſs in the World, or endeavour to increaſe their Eſtates, as appears by ſo vaſt a Multitude of Eſtates ſo deeply Mortgaged, which hath brought Landed Men in general out of Credit. Add to this, That while Gentlemen have the Diſpoſal of their Eſtates, and can privately engage them to others for Debts, no Man can be ſo ſecure of dealing with, or truſting any Landed Man.</p>
            <p>If then it be ſo, that Diligence, Carefulneſs and Exactneſs, be the real and true Cauſe of increaſing and ſupporting Credit, then it muſt follow, that when Gentlemens Eſtates are publickly made oyer in Truſt to an Office of Credit, for ſo many years certain, to
<pb facs="tcp:51040:5"/>anſwer all Bills of Credit iſſued thereupon, or any Sums of Money depoſited therein, and that this Office be exact in their Times and Payments; the Credit of this Office muſt, in Proportion, far exceed that of any Goldſmith whatſoever, though never ſo careful; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the Land is the beſt and ſureſt Fund (and ſo, much the better, when aſſiſted by a Stock in Trade as aforeſaid) neither can the Land be ever alienated or appropriated to any other uſe, than to make good their Bills and Payments.</p>
            <p>There will be more Care, Exactneſs and Diligence uſed for Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>provement of the Joint Stock, than can be by any particular Trader whatſoever; and a large Controul to hinder or correct whatſoever is done amiſs. Beſides, the Books and Accounts will lie open to the view of all Men, which a Shop-keeper will not diſcover; and if he Breaks, or Dies, as too many have done, where is the certainty of the Fund, or what hopes that ever you ſhall have your Money again? Whereas the Office cannot die.</p>
            <p>At the end of the 4th Year, the whole Sum of 10000 <hi>l.</hi> will be given out on every 150 <hi>l. per Annum,</hi> and before that, will begin the time of Recalling and Cancelling the Bills yearly for Rent to the Office, and will be continued every year till the time expires; by which Method the number of Bills will yearly be leſſened, and the Secu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity will thereby become every year the better. And the Bills having been thus diſpers'd amongſt not only the Subſcribers, but their Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nants and Friends, and likewiſe to the Joynt Stock, and Charges of the Undertaking, the 10000 <hi>l.</hi> can never be ſuppoſed to be brought in all at once to be Exchanged for Money, any more than any Gold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſmith's or Bank of <hi>England</hi>'s Notes, whoſe Fund few queſtions, tho' not near ſo certain, or are unwilling to give them Credit; and why more ſhould be expected of this Office, than of any other in the World, is very unreaſonable to imagine; but all Men will not be of one and the ſame mind with our Dialogue-Monger, it being not Caſe of a Mortgager, that hath to do but with one Man, who will have all his Money called in at once.</p>
            <p>The Joynt Stock in Trade will likewiſe greatly aſſiſt to keep the Bills in Motion, and poſſibly as well as if they were all preſently turned into Money: Since therefore all theſe aforeſaid Perſons do agree to Encourage and Promote the paſſing of the Bills, to be ſure they will not bring, nor ſend any more to the Office, than juſt to ſerve their Occaſions for Market or Pocket Expences; ſo that they will not, nor indeed can at once all be brought in for Money to prejudice the Office; nor can the Office fail, as this Author hopes and wiſhes, tho' he and ſome others of his Malicious Crew may bring
<pb facs="tcp:51040:6"/>in as many Bills as they can, to endeavour the Deſtruction of it, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe their number may be but few and inconſiderable; and as long as there are Landed Men and Traders enough, who will approve the Security, and promote the Bills, and ſupply the Office with Caſh, and that with much more than the Office may have occaſion for, we need not trouble our ſelves about ſuch ſhallow-Brain'd Fellows as this Dialogue-Monger. For it is not expected, that in its In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fancy every body will approve of it; as for Example, all timerous Men that will neither truſt Goldſmiths, Banks, or any body elſe, Subſcribers in other Banks, obſtinate Blockheads, that will not un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand the way of either, and prejudiced Perſons, ſuch as our Dead-doing Dialogue-Monger, may Fooliſhly or Maliciouſly Reject it; yet if we meet with as many more other ſort of People that will, of which the Dr. has reaſon not to doubt, it will ſtill ſufficiently an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer all our Ends: For no Man that opens his Shop, can expect all People will buy of him; but if ſo many do, as he is enabled there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by, to keep his Family, pay his Rent and Debts, it is all he deſires. This, I hope, will ſatisfie any Rational Man, that the Bills cannot, nor is there reaſon they ſhould, be brought in all at once to the Office, nor can there be any want of Money to anſwer thoſe Bills that are brought, as this Dialogue vainly ſuggeſts. To proceed then with our Punner, after he hath made the Dr. anſwer what he pleaſes, he tells him, <hi>That he makes a Part to be greater than the Whole, and a Term to be more worth than a Fee Simple, which is ſimple all over.</hi> But how Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pertinent he is to make the Dr. who never aſſirmed any ſuch thing, to ſpeak thus abſurdly, is already ſhewed, where mention is made of the 22500 <hi>l.</hi> being Security for 10000 <hi>l.</hi> Beſides, it is not very ſtrange for one Perſon by his Induſtry, to improve a Part ſo, as to yield more, than others have made the Whole at any time before.</p>
            <p>The next thing therefore to be obſerved, is, our Malapert Squires Remarks on the little Sum the Dr. hath propoſed to circulate the Bills: And here, tho' at firſt he hath repeated the Dr's Method of rai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing more plenty of Money, than any other Bank does allow, to cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culate the Bills; yet at laſt he would have all Men take ſpecial no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice, that there neither is in the Office, nor ever will be, any more than juſt 100 <hi>l.</hi> to circulate 1100 <hi>l.</hi> in Bills; and ſlily inſinuates, as if all this 1100 <hi>l.</hi> in Bills were in one Man's Hands, or in ſeveral, that ſhould agree together to keep the Bills four years together, and then carry them all at once into the Office to be preſently Exchanged for Money in Specie, and then concludes, that without the Spirit of Prophecy he foretells this Bank will ſoon be at an end; ay, I warrant you, before it be begun. But how does this Mr Foreſight know it
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:51040:6"/>will all fall out ſo exactly as he ſays? For as he does not tell this by the Spirit of Prophecy, ſo neither do I take him to be any great Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jurer, or elſe he might have foreſeen, that all his Fallacy would eaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly be Detected, and his Objections Anſwered, and then would have ſaved all the Pains and Charges of making and printing this Senſeleſs Dialogue.</p>
            <p>I hope, that to any Unprejudiced Attentive Reader, I have ſhewed plainly before, that it is impoſſible that all the Bills ſhould be brought in at once, as this Country Squire would have it; and likewiſe that it is highly probable, that this Office may, and will be truſted with as much or more running Caſh, beſides what the Dr. propoſes to be depoſited by the Subſcribers, as any Goldſmith or other Bank now is, or can be; if ſo, as there is little doubt, then will this Office have much more than 500000 <hi>l.</hi> in Money to Exchange what Tickets ſhall be deſired. But ſays our Gent. (after he hath ſo Falla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciouſly ſtated the State) <hi>Thoſe who have ſo little Wit as to ſettle their Eſtates in ſuch a Bank, will deſerve to have their Eſtates begg'd, if they do not make a ſure Game on't, for to be ſure, firſt come, firſt ſerv'd; and how ſimply will a Man look, when he comes with his Tickets, and finds the Birds flown, his Money gone, and no Security remaining for his Money</hi>— This Gent. would have every body underſtand the Dr's Bank after his manner only, and no better than as this thick Scull'd Animal (to uſe his Terms) does himſelf, not conſidering, that all his Objections have been already made, fully anſwered, and rightly underſtood, by all ſuch as are concerned, before they Subſcribe their Eſtates to it; who, it may well be preſumed, are ſo throughly ſenſible of the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and goodneſs of the Deſign of it, as to have a little more Wit than either to be aſhamed, or to repent, or be frighted out of their Subſcriptions on ſight of this inſipid Scribble; inſomuch that ſince this Dialogue hath been diſperſt, moſt of the particulars of their Eſtates have been ſent into the Agent in order to their Settlement; and do underſtand before hand, that ſuch a Game cannot be play'd as this ſharp Gent. would have them, there being not Bills to the value of the Eſtate given out at firſt; for this is an Office of Land Credit, and not like <hi>Briſco</hi>'s, <hi>Barebone</hi>'s, or <hi>Royal Bank,</hi> or any other Monied Bank, that hath no other Fund to anſwer its Bills of Credit, but what is depoſited in Specie, which as ſoon as ever it is all drawn out, does preſently put an end to the Bank it ſelf; even as the old Banking Goldſmiths in <hi>Lombard ſtreet</hi> were ruin'd when the <hi>Exchequer</hi> was ſhut up; they having ſettled no Fund of Land to anſwer ſo many Bills as they had given out, ſo that only thoſe were paid, who came firſt for their Money, and many others left unpaid to this day, to
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:51040:7"/>their Ruine: Whereas if Eſtates had been ſettled after the Dr's man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner for the Payment of the Bills, they would never have crowded ſo faſt for their Money; and all their Bills might have been paid off before this time, by an <hi>Annual Payment</hi> out of the ſaid Eſtates; and ſuppoſe the worſt, that it ſhould be the Caſe of this Bank, as this Prevaricating Gentleman would have it, that all the Birds are flown, and his Money gone, yet ſtill the Bills, for which his Money was paid, will be found there; and thoſe Bills will be ſo well ſecured, as either to be readily curernt, or be certainly anſwered by Virtue of their Land Security; ſo that if a Man brings Bills, and miſſes ready Money for them juſt at that inſtant (which is unlikely to happen) he is not preſently undone, neither hath ſo much cauſe to look ſimple, becauſe he keeps his Eſtate, which is the Security for the Bills, in his own Hands, and pays his Rent or Annuity in the Bills that lie by him, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the Propoſals; For his Eſtate is not loſt, or to be ſold, or fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cloſed, having no Debts to pay, elſe he cannot bring in all the 10000 <hi>l.</hi> Bills at four years end to be Exchanged: If he has Debts, then certainly they will be paid by the Office in four years time, there being Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney and Bills of Credit ſufficient (as in other Banks) in that time, and for that purpoſe; but if after all, this Bank muſt be at an end, by reaſon of the Bills being all at a glut called for, to be changed into Money preſently; why then there may as well be an end of all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Bills of Credit alſo, upon a like run upon them for Money; ſince all our end of Credit was only or chiefly contrived to ſupply the want of Money; and ſo there would be neither Goldſmiths or Bank, or other Credit whatſoever, nor could any Banks in the World ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt, if all their Credit muſt be paid off at once, and that as ſoon as given out. It ought to be a great ſatisfaction to the World, that Eſtates are tied to make good all Bills of Credit in ſuch a certain term of years, in a manner ſufficient to make good what is under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taken. And therefore the Bills may very well be current in the mean time. As for his adding; <hi>After his Money is gone, and no Security remaining for his Money;</hi> it is Nonſenſe, and Contradiction to ſay that, when juſt before he called them Fools, for tying their Eſtates to ſuch a Bank; for if any Eſtates are tied, then there is a remaining Security. In the next place, ſuch affirming, there is no Security, is not an Objection to the Dr's Bank, but a direct giving himſelf the Lye, having (as juſt before) confeſſed the contrary, that the Dr. does Propoſe, that Eſtates ſhall be tied for ſo many as 100 years certain, to pay yearly for the Bills. This is not like <hi>Briſco</hi>'s or <hi>Barebone</hi>'s Banks, where they Propoſe to lend 1500 <hi>l.</hi> on 100 <hi>l per Annum,</hi> and further give out Bills of Credit upon the ſame Eſtate, and the Gent.
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:51040:7"/>take leave to pay in his Money at any time, and redeem his Eſtate; and when theſe ſaid Banks are repaid all the Money they have lent on many Eſtates, and delivered up the Deeds, if they ſhould run away with the Money; pray who ſhould anſwer for the Bills, when the Eſtates that were the Security are releaſed, they being not tied for any years certain? Or what an hopeful Bargain ſhall ſuch have, who depoſit their Money as running Caſh in ſuch Banks, where the Secu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity is ſo uncertain?</p>
            <p>But again, Suppoſing there is no Money left in the Office, yet it can never Break or be Ruined, or any Man be undone by it; for that the Land is tied to bay off, in order to be Cancelled, ſo many Bills every year, of any Perſon that has them, ſo that by degrees they will all be paid for; the Dr's Propoſal being to ſet up an Office of Land Credit, and not a Money Bank, though Money will not be wanting to aſſiſt the needful Circulation of the Bills of Credit.</p>
            <p>Our Civil Countrey Gent. makes the Dr. Correct him for his un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mannerly Expreſſions, which though he deſign'd a Jeſt, yet may be applied in earneſt, and cauſe enough, when he ſo ungentlemanly queſtions the Verity of Great Mens being at all concerned in the Dr's Undertaking, and accuſes the Dr. of unwarrantably making uſe of the Names of Perſons of the firſt Rank, as concerned with him in his Bank; whether the Dr. have ſo done, any Man may ſee by their Subſcriptions, and when the Conſtitution of the Bank is Publiſhed, it will appear beyond Contradiction. But ſtill the Gent. harps on the ſame ſtring, and like a Brother of <hi>Jerry Squirts,</hi> muſt repeat the ſame thing over and over again. <hi>Doctor, I ſay your Bank muſt fall, becauſe you have no Security.</hi> For which, Mr <hi>Thick-Scull,</hi> we have on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly your bare word; but juſt after the ſame manner, did Scrivener <hi>Blake</hi> repeat the ſame thing ſeveral times, which was fully anſwered in the <hi>Rod for the Fool's back:</hi> But that Book falling into but ſew Hands, I ſhall therefore anſwer it here again, by repeating the an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer there given, <hi>viz. The Doctor never affihmed it to be a Security, for all the Credit to be paid off in one Sum, as when Eſtates are propoſed to be ſold;</hi> there being no ſuch Deſign here: nor is it poſſible to bring in all the Five Millions of Credit to be Exchanged, becauſe the Stock will always have a large Sum for their uſe; and nothing can poſſibly make the Bank fall, unleſs the Subſcribers and Governors of the Joynt Stock will all agree together to deſtroy that, which they have taken ſo much care all this while to ſet up, and which if not encouraged, will certainly be the Ruin of many of them, whoſe Eſtates are deeply engaged, there being not Money enough by a tenth part to be had in the Nation to free their Eſtates; which other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:51040:8"/>will be devoured by the Monied Perſons and Uſurers, who are ſo Mercileſs as to Impriſon their Debtors, Seize their Eſtates, fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cloſe the Equity of Redemption, and leave the Landed Men and their Families to ſtarve; and except killing them, our Enemies the <hi>French</hi> can do no more: And therefore its the Intereſt of all other Landed Men, as well as the Subſcribers to this Office, to promote the Bills of Credit on Land, ſince Money cannot be had, for the better ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port of their Families, and the preſervation of the Value of their Lands, and in their own Defence to run Counter to all unfair Dea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers in Money, and ſhake off their heavy Yoak of Bondage, by en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaging their Lands after this manner, and making it perform the uſe of Money, as well as Gold or Silver when Coyn'd; and thus to buy off the Bills by an Annual eaſie Payment; and for other reaſons likewiſe, as that there are more Landed Men than Monied Men in the Nation, and a greater Value of Land than Money, which Money is but the Product of this Land. The Landed Men have chiefly contributed to the ſupport of this War, do want Money moſt, and are leaſt e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteemed; the Land remains a ſure Fund, when Money or Commodities are carried away, worn out, or periſhed; and the Trader may bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter afford to take the Bills, than let any Perſon run in Debt on his Book three or four or more years, and then receive a part, and truſt for more, which if the Debtor dies, the Debt is hazzarded, and many times loſt, and as oft put to the trouble of a Law Suit, but the Office will not die, and his Account will no more be with the Debtor, but with the Office, which will either ſatisfie him, or take care to make the Land do it. Therefore I tell you again, that it is a good Security as the Dr. hath propoſed it, for all the Credit that will be given out thereupon; and will anſwer all that will be brought to the Office for Money. But what matter is it what ſuch a ſorry ſharping Fellow as this ſays, that hath neither Name or Senſe? And yet, for that it's poſſible, that ſuch Creatures, like ſecret Villains, may do a great deal of miſchief, tho' never any good; therefore it's convenient to give an anſwer, both to cure and prevent the Evils he endeavours to Promote; for ſo he would hinder all Perſons from giving any the leaſt Credit, or depoſiting any Caſh, when he tells you, that he who pays 100 <hi>l.</hi> into your Bank, will have a hope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful bargain of it; ſince he does not like it, he ſhould have told us what Goldſmith or Bank gives a better Security, or where all Men ſhould put their Money ſafely: But why is this Gent. ſo much con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerned that Men ſhould not truſt their Money here? If he does not like it, he may keep his Money, for there is no compulſion on him to bring it hither; and yet I think thoſe Men do much more deſerve to have their Eſtates begg'd, who will ſubſcribe to any other Bank
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:51040:8"/>that will lend them but 1500 <hi>l.</hi> on 100 <hi>l. per Annum,</hi> which they cannot repay in ſo many years; when this Bank will ſupply them with ſo much more than will pay their Debts, and as much again to Trade withal: But ſuppoſe now, that there is a Million of running Caſh in ſeve-Goldſmiths Hands, and other Banks in <hi>London,</hi> may it not be with as much ſafety put in here, where an Office will be more regularly formed than any where elſe? And may not the Bills of this Bank, which cannot be ſo eaſily counterfeited as any others, be as good to give for that Caſh as any they give? And is not the Security much better, ſince the Land is tied for ſo many years certain, to an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer the Bills, if any accidental loſs ſhould happen? Does any Gold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſmith give you any other Security than his bare Note, and that without Intereſt too, for what Caſh you pay him? And may not this Office, that hath ſo many Landed Eſtates to ſecure their Bills, thrive as well, and be as reſponſible with the running Caſh it ſhall be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>truſted with, as any particular Trader whatſoever? But to proceed, he makes the Doctor ſay, <hi>The Subſcribers will favour the Bank:</hi> Well, and what then? If they do, it will be more than this Sharper, joyn'd with all the Crew of his Malicious Companions, can do to hinder them, or deſtroy the Bank, becauſe the Bills will be all in their own Diſpoſal and Management; but ſaith our Sharper, <hi>What do you talk of favouring the Bank? We live in a ſharp Age, wherein every one will favour himſelf, and will ſecure</hi> 80 <hi>years Purchaſe for</hi> 100 l. <hi>a year if he can get it;</hi> I told you what a Sharper we had got, this looks ſo exactly like <hi>Jo. Briſcoe,</hi> that one would ſwear 'twas his nown very ſelf; and perhaps there may be three or four ſuch Sharpers crept in amongſt our Subſcribers, that may draw out what they can on their Eſtates; which if they do, that will not break the Bank: But they cannot make ſo ſure a Game on't as he imagines, for the Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcriber can have but fifty years Purchaſe, if he raiſeth the Circula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion Money, and but forty if he does not; and for that he muſt ſtay four years firſt, the reſt being in Stock, <hi>&amp;c</hi> and afterwards let him do his worſt, for by that time the price of Land will advance to more than forty years Purchaſe; ſo that he may not be able to mend himſelf after he has his Money, however his Eſtate will be ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cured, which is as much as the Office expects. And tho' theſe Shar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers draw out all the Caſh they can, may it not be allowed that other fair dealing Men and Approvers of the Bank, (and perhaps thoſe to whom the Sharpers pay Money too) may bring in as much running Caſh to aſſiſt the Bank as well, and as is done every day in Goldſmiths Shops? Or muſt they firſt ask our Sharpers leave, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther they ſhall bring it hither or no? However, to prevent falling,
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:51040:9"/>he makes the Doctor ſay, <hi>No more Tickets ſhall be delivered out than there is Money to Anſwer: Of what uſe then, ſaith our fine Gent. will the Bank be?</hi> O Sir, by your leave, of very great uſe, even ſuch as young Goldſmiths make, <hi>viz.</hi> to beget a good Credit with all People, for that trick will be plaid at firſt, that all timerous Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, as well as Traders, may be aſſured there is ſafe dealing with the Office and their Bills; and to prevent all ſuch Sharpers, as you are, from making us to fall, as but now you ſaid we muſt; and after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards when we know it's out of your power to hurt us, then in imita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation of all other Traders and Banks, we will give out the reſt of our Credit; but yet, not more than is allowed by Propoſal, tho' all others do. But ſaith the Gent. <hi>Pray, Doctor, what neceſſity was there for you to exceed your Fund by Iſſuing out</hi> 10000 l. <hi>upon</hi> 150 l. <hi>a year?</hi> Why truly Sir, the reaſon of exceeding the Term, for the Fund is not exceeded, is, that every Subſcriber ſhould be ſo well gratified for engaging his Eſtate to make good the Bills of this Office, for ſo long a Term, as ſhould enable him not only to pay all his Debts, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vide well for his Family; but to lay by enough for a Joynt Stock, the Profits whereof will repay the whole eaſily, both Principle and Intereſt, and all this without any fear or danger of being Areſted, Impriſoned, Forecloſed, or Eſtates ſeized and ſold; being a moſt Noble Deſign to free Landed Men out of the Clutches of griping Uſurers, Attorneys, Scriveners, Bayliffs and Goal-keepers; who, as a Gent. hath deſcrib'd in his <hi>Character of the Devil in Maſquerade,</hi> are worſe than <hi>Turks</hi> and <hi>Pagans</hi> to the Debtor, becauſe they cannot do Impoſſibilities, and pay great Sums out of nothing; to which Difficulties many are reduced by the ſeveral Alterations, Miſfortunes, and Accidents in our Government, at the ſame time when we want Men in the Countrey to Till the Ground and gather in our Harveſt, to ſupply our Armies and Navies, when there are above 30000 able Men Priſoners in ſeveral Goals; but twice the number of little Petty Foggers and their Attendants of Catch-poles, Gaolers and their ſeveral Hangers on, who all ſuck the very Heart-blood of theſe mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerable Captives, and the Cruel Creditor never the better, but ſtill purſuing his Severity, till theſe Harpies has emptied his Pockets, and reduced him to the ſame wretched Condition; and beſides, pray conſider what an ill Cuſtom we have, when a Landed Man in neceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, Mortgages 150 <hi>l.</hi> a year for 1000 <hi>l.</hi> that on half a years notice at any time after its become due, on non-payment of Intereſt, or Caprice of the Mortgagee, all this Money ſhall be called in, and if not paid, tho' not to be procured, then preſently to Impriſon, Fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cloſe <hi>&amp;c.</hi> when as the Mortgagee is as much obliged to the other for
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:51040:9"/>the Intereſt, as the Mortgager to him for his Money; but this Office will put an End to ſuch Abuſes, and alſo raiſe the Value of Land; ay, and will alſo undertake to pay off the 1200000 <hi>l.</hi> to the Royal Bank in Earneſt, and make good all the Clipt Money too, tho' our Gent. makes but a Jeſt on't, if a little more be added to the Fund made to the Royal Bank. But the better to ſhew the Neceſſity of ſo large a Credit, I will preſent you with a view of ſomething like the preſent ſtate of the Nation,</p>
            <p>In <hi>Charles</hi> the Second's Days, the Number of Families, according to the Accounts of the Books of Hearth-money, were 1300000, of which, 500000 were poor, and could not pay Taxes; ſo that the Burthen lay wholly on the remaining 800000; of theſe it may be reaſonably computed ſince this War, that 150000 are either be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come incapable of paying their proportions, as before, or make an hard ſhift to pay more than they can well ſpare, to keep up their ſmall Credit, and in a little time may fall into the ſame Number of Poor; ſo then remains but 750000 Families to pay Taxes, which is but one half of the Nation; of theſe it may again be conſidered, that 450000 are indebted, and have mortgaged their Eſtates to the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maining 300000 Families, who make the others pay all Taxes on their Lands and Moneys borrowed; and now ſince Money is not to be had, the Mortgagees take Advantage of the preſent Neceſſity, and impriſon the Mortgagers, fore cloſe, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> to the ruine of many a Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mily; there being no Remedy left, but raiſing Credit on Land. For if Peace were now proclaimed, it is a queſtion if all the Creditors will wait for their Money till it be brought in by plenty of Trade; but at the laſt, what ſhall become of Priſoners, and the Poor, that have nothing to pay? Now let it be conſidered, that the greateſt part of Trade is carried on by Credit, there being not above 50 <hi>l.</hi> or 100 <hi>l.</hi> paid down, when 1000 <hi>l.</hi> at leaſt is left to be paid ſix, 12, or 18 Months hence, for which the Seller hath no other Security or Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurance, than the honeſt Word and Credit of the Chapman; who ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times fails, or continues a long Account, which perhaps is left to be ended by his Executors. And ſince the greateſt part of Traders, as well as Landed-Men, are neceſſitated to uſe Credit, how much ſafer is it to uſe <hi>Bills of Credit,</hi> thus ſafely ſecured, which might preſently be given, and thereby put an end to all long Accounts?</p>
            <p>Further, You ſhall hear what <hi>Jo. Briſcoe</hi>'s Opinion is, in anſwer to Uſurer, p. 3d. <hi>Can any thing be more juſt and honeſt, than for Gentlemen to meet together to conſider which way the Freeholders of</hi> England, <hi>(who have upon all occaſions contributed largely towards carrying on the War, and ſupport of the Government, while the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſurer hath paid little or nothing for
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:51040:10"/>Taxes) may be able to pay their Debts, and clear off their Incumbrances, by raiſing a Credit out of their Freehold Eſtates? And may they not as rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonably expect a Credit ſhould be given them upon ſuch their Eſtates, as others have upon far leſs Securities, and thereby reſcue themſelves and Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>milies from impending ruine?</hi> But our Gentleman being of another Opinion, does ask, <hi>What if but</hi> 10 <hi>or</hi> 15 <hi>years, inſtead of</hi> 100 <hi>years Pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſe, had been iſſued out upon Eſtates?</hi> By this Queſtion, I ſhould judge <hi>Briſcoe,</hi> or his Friend Mr. <hi>Weſt,</hi> or one of their Directors, to be the <hi>Querent,</hi> and that he is affraid the Doctor<hi>'s Great Bank</hi> ſhould ſwallow up his <hi>Little One:</hi> But however, to ſatisfie him, I anſwer, That to raiſe but 15 years Purchaſe, is to ſupply a Man but by halves; as when a Friend lends a Trader 1000 <hi>l.</hi> to pay his ſeveral Creditors, it makes him eaſie for the preſent; yet afterwards the Trader will find it as hard to repay this Friend, as the Creditors before; but if his Friend lends him 2000 <hi>l.</hi> he will then have a commanding Stock, be able to buy Goods at the beſt rate with ready Money, and give longer Credit; and ſo will be better able to repay the 2000 <hi>l.</hi> than ever he can the 1000 <hi>l.</hi> And therefore your Propoſal of 15 years purchaſe, is but ſhift<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Burthen from one Shoulder to the other; or rather it is a plain deſign to keep the <hi>Freeholders Necks</hi> ſtill under the Yoak, for the increaſing the Loan of the Principal to five years Purchaſe more than is uſually lent, is equivalent to 6 <hi>per Cent.</hi> Intereſt, when it comes to be repaid; and ſo both <hi>Barebone</hi>'s and the National Land Bank, will be equally as prejudicial in the end, as the Uſurers before; for if you do not pay your Intereſt exact, tho' but ſmall, then they will ſell your Eſtate; neither can they afford to let their Money out at 3 <hi>per Cent.</hi> without the help of Bills of Credit; and if they let out Bills to all the Freeholders that would borrow, then they will not have Money enough to anſwer them, and their Banks muſt fall as the Gent. ſays the <hi>Doctor</hi>'s muſt; but if under a Colour they give but 15 years Purchaſe, the better to gain their <hi>Bills</hi> a Credit, becauſe the Security is judged ſufficient, and thereupon iſſue out <hi>Bills</hi> to 2 or 300 years Purchaſe, without Limitation, having no Check upon them, then they will be worſe than the <hi>Doctor</hi>'s <hi>Office,</hi> the utmoſt of whoſe Credit is known, and they may prove in the end fatal to the Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment: If all their 15 years <hi>Bills</hi> be brought preſently to be exchan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged for ready Money, as is objected againſt the Doctor of his 10000 <hi>l. Bills;</hi> then this Objection lies as ſtrong againſt their Banks as the <hi>Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctor</hi>'s, and there is an end of Credit; and then there will not be ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient to pay the Charges of the Rent, and Sallaries of the Offices; and no Man will lend his Money at 3, when he can make 5 or 6 <hi>per Cent.</hi> of it.</p>
            <pb n="19" facs="tcp:51040:10"/>
            <p>Beſides, ſince its neceſſary to raiſe Credit, to ſupply the want of Money, its convenient to fix on a certain Term of Years that may raiſe ſo much Credit as may pay the Debts due, and likewiſe keep a Man from running into Debt again, and a little to provide for his Family; which 15 years Credit will not do, and pay the Charges of the Office: And in compariſon to the vaſt Credit Goldſmiths and and other Banks give, beyond their Value or Ability to pay, this may be judged but a moderate Credit, which in a reaſonable time may be anſwered by Trade, as well as made good by Land; and if more Credit were advanced, by extending the term 50, or 100 years lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, then ſo many Perſons could not have the benefit thereof. The great difference between this Office and other Banks and Goldſmiths, as to Credit and running Caſh, conſiſts in this, That thoſe latter lie ſcat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered about the Town, &amp; give only their bare Notes for Money, which is Perſonal Security only, without any other Fund, and their Bills are without limitation: Whereas this will be a well-regulated Office, contrived to do all their Buſineſs with much more Care and Exact<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, will have an Unqueſtionable Controul and Check upon them, to prevent giving out any more Bills than are to be according to the Propoſals; and will alſo have a ſure Fund in Land, which cannot be releas'd, till all the Bills given out thereon are bought up and can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell'd. But our Gentleman being very cunning, at laſt hath found out, That the Doctors chief Deſign was, after he had made his Bank profitable to thoſe concerned in it, that then it ſhould be ſo to him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf: Well deviſed, Old <hi>Noſtradamus!</hi> And if the <hi>Doctor</hi> had not ſo contrived it, I ſhould have taken him for a more Thick-Scull'd Ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mal than this our Gentleman, who ſo much envies the <hi>Doctor</hi>'s Gains, as he would willingly make that Objection ſufficient to hinder any Subſcriber from coming into the Doctor's Office: And tho' the <hi>Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctor</hi> gets never ſo much, yet the Subſcriber's Advantage will be five times greater in this Office, than he can hope to get in any other Bank whatſoever.</p>
            <p>He is pleas'd to reproach the <hi>Doctor,</hi> as guilty of the greateſt Act of Preſumption, for inſinuating, <hi>That ſuch Perſons as Miniſters of State, ſhould come to him for Wages, as if they were his Journeymen or Lacquies;</hi> and this in print too: Why truly, Sir, This Reproof ſhould have come a little ſooner, for now the Jeſt of it is quite ſpoil'd, becauſe ſome of them did well approve of the Propoſal before your Dialogue came abroad, and others of them ſince have given it their Approbation; and think it not unbecoming their Dignities, to ſee that ſo great and publick a Good be rightly managed and applied: So, Sir, I hope you will not be much offended at the <hi>Doctor,</hi> ſince they
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:51040:11"/>are pleaſed. All this it ſeems was fully anſwered in the <hi>Rod for the Ecols Back,</hi> as this Gentleman is ſenſible by his Quotation, and ſo needed not be repeated by him again, but that I find he is of the ſame humour with the <hi>Iriſh-man,</hi> who when asked if he did not ſee the Kings Flag on top? Anſwered, <hi>Iſh by my Shoul, dear Joy, Iſh did ſee it plain enough; but Iſh would not ſee it.</hi> He makes the <hi>Doctor</hi> to ſpeak after his manner, and patch'd up a Diſcourſe with a piece out of one Book, and a ſcrap out of another, to make it ſerve for his pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, well knowing that few Perſons have thoſe Books (which he hath quoted) by them, or that they will give themſelves the trouble to ſee how he had diſ-joynted the Diſcourſe, and made the Senſe of it imperfect, by leaving that behind, which would otherwiſe be a full Anſwer to his Objections. Next, he will needs make the <hi>Doctor</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolve to have him ſubſcribe his Eſtate in his Bank, which in good man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners he refuſeth, for that he knoweth better things: And if the ſaid Gentlemans Name was known, I believe that neither the <hi>Doctor</hi> nor his Managers, would deſire ſuch a Thick-Scull'd Animal to come amongſt them; Notwithſtanding he pretends to have 150 <hi>l. per annum,</hi> as good as ever Crow flew over, which perhaps is only in <hi>Nubibus</hi> neither; I ſcarce believe he is Owner of a Dog-Kennel, rather of nothing at all. As for his pleaſant Romantick Diſcourſe of improving his Eſtate to an hundred times more than the <hi>Doctor</hi>'s Propoſal offers, and his making the <hi>Doctor</hi> to offer to ſcour his Kettle for being delirious; I do not indeed take him to be ſo, but rather that Monkey-like he prettily endeavours to Ape the Doctor, and may be as fitting a Perſon for a Jack-Pudding to a Puppet-Shew, in <hi>Bartholomew</hi>-Fair, to draw the Mob to the Door, as ever I heard of; for their Diſcourſe is exactly of a piece with this, and after the very ſame manner; and leaſt he ſhould want a livelihood in the mean time, I'll ſpeak to the <hi>Doctor</hi> that there may be a place reſerved on purpoſe, and a ſmall Sallary for him, that this Ridiculer of what he wants Brains to underſtand, may find ſo much favour from the <hi>Doctor</hi>'s Generous Hand, as (inſtead of Puniſhment for his lewd Scurrility) to be pardoned, and admitted Buffoon to the Bank.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="postscript">
            <pb n="21" facs="tcp:51040:11"/>
            <head>POSTSCRIPT.</head>
            <p>J<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>st now I hear that Mr. <hi>National Briſcoe</hi> and Dr. <hi>Barebone</hi> are joyn'd together: A very great <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nion indeed! It ſeems to argue that neither of them did well know how to proceed alone; or ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, that they were afraid Dr. <hi>Chamberlen</hi>'s Office of Land Credit would ſwallow them both up, and ſo I believe it will, notwithſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing all their Craft and Subtilty, with their Purſes joyn'd together. But its worth while to reflect a little on the past Actions of this pair of Bankers—Dr. <hi>Barebone</hi> firſt ſets up a Land-Bank, pretending to help the poor diſtreſſed Freeholders; which when <hi>Briſcoe</hi> ſaw, he preſently tells the World that <hi>Barebone</hi> ſtole his Propoſals from out of his Book, which is very unreaſonable; and therefore he will now ſet it on foot, and call it a National Land Bank: <hi>Barebone,</hi> to deſtroy that Project, puts forth another Paper, and calls it, <hi>The Freeholders Anſwer to</hi> Briſcoe<hi>'s National Land Bank,</hi> to which <hi>Briſcoe</hi> Prints a Reply; in both which Papers they reflect on each others Reputation; and what Cauſe they had ſo to do, I am ſenſible the World in part underſtands; and enough was ſaid to let the World ſee plainly they were <hi>Birds of a Feather,</hi> and therefore in all Probability would not be long aſunder. But thus both theſe for a conſiderable while have pretended to be the firſt Setters up of a Land Bank, when all the World knows they are both a Brace of Notable Plagiaries, and have built on Dr. <hi>Chamberlen</hi>'s Foundation, only both of them find it difficult enough to ſet up, form, or manage ſo great a Concern as a Land Bank, and that made them unite toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, to try if they might then do any better Feats, for that they un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand Dr. <hi>Chamberlen</hi>'s Office is coming on by degrees to be too hard for them: But after theſe aforeſaid Plagiaries have been ſo long expoſing and ridiculing each other; at laſt <hi>Briſcoe</hi> begins to ſneak to <hi>Barebones</hi> for ſhelter, finding that his Subſcribers of both Land and Money, could not agree; and Dr. <hi>Chamberlen</hi>'s Print<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:51040:12"/>
               <hi>Briſcoe</hi>'s Letter, formerly writ in Commendation of his Bank, did not further ſuch Agreement; ſo that inſtead of having <hi>1000</hi> l. <hi>per annum</hi> during Life, and a large round ſum beſides, he muſt be glad to accept of a Salary from <hi>Barebone,</hi> perhaps of <hi>40</hi> or <hi>50</hi> l. <hi>per annum:</hi> And last of all, after they have both bemoaned and expoſed the ſad and deplorable Condition of the poor Freeholder, with large Aſſurances of Aſſistance, they both have agreed to ſupply the Government with Two Millions for a Branch of the Revenue, and ſo leave the poor Freeholder in a more wretched ruinous Condition than before, to make his Peace with his Creditors as well as he can.</p>
            <p>Well! It's pity but they ſhould always be joyn'd together, and how well ſoever they may deſerve of the Government for their good Service, yet if they do not likewiſe ſupply the poor Freeholder, after all theſe large Promiſes, and buſtle made, why then I think that the very ſight of theſe two Whimſical Plagiaries will be a Cauſe ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent for every Freeholder to ſpue them out of their company: And for the Freeholders Comfort, Dr. <hi>Chamberlen</hi>'s Office will be ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, and put in a Condition fully to help them out of all their Engage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, according as his Propoſals do ſet forth.</p>
            <div type="part">
               <p>WHile I am writing this, out comes another Propoſal of a Crown Bank, being a very ſafe and eaſie Method for ſupplying the want of Coin to ſerve the Publick Occaſion; humbly offered, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Ay ſure! But as to private Occaſions, 'tis no matter what becomes of the People; if they are all impriſoned or ſtarved, that's nothing; for ſo a Man would judge, when he ſays at the latter end, <hi>This has its certain Limits, and reaches no farther than the Neceſſities of the Publick require:</hi> And this Author fancies himſelf, I believe, the firſt Propoſer of this refined Method; but I can tell him of one Mr. <hi>William Killegrew,</hi> that put a Propoſal in Print of the ſame nature, ſome years ago, from whom this Man hath ſtole his, after the ſame manner as <hi>Briſcoe</hi> has done his National Land Bank from Dr. <hi>Chamberlen.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>By his Remarks on the other Banks, he ſeems to underſtand nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of them very well, but eſpecially that of Dr. <hi>Chamberlens,</hi> which he calls a Myſtery at firſt, and ſo he may very well; for, by his miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>repreſentation of it, it ſeems to be much above the Capacity of his
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:51040:12"/>weak Noddle to comprehend, and therefore to him is a great Myſtery.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>John Briſcoe</hi> perceiving there were a great multitude of ſuch ſhal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low-brain'd Creatures in the Nation, did therefore contrive his Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſals on purpoſe for them, and call'd it <hi>A National Land-Bank,</hi> and this Author (as I am inform'd) is one of <hi>Briſcoe</hi>'s Subſcribers (as his long Diſcourſe in praiſe of <hi>Briſcoe</hi>'s Bank does ſeem to imply) and yet, as fair as he has repreſented it, in Page the 7th, in his Remarks to Object. 2d, he ſays, <hi>For if neither can extend its Credit beyond the Money in Bank, or advanc'd in ſpecie, it were to no purpoſe to pretend to a Bank of Credit;</hi> and this he will allow to be done in <hi>Briſcoe</hi>'s Bank, that propoſes no Limits to his Bills; but not in the <hi>Doctor</hi>'s, whoſe Bills are limited: And yet in the beginning of his Pamphlet, does preſume that the Parliament will give a Check to that endleſs in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe of Bills of Credit, which upon the Failure of any of the Banks to anſwer in ſpecie, when generally call'd for, may prove a greater miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chief than that which they would remedy: Which tacitly condemns <hi>Briſcoe</hi>'s Deſign, to give out Bills without number, as he ſays of the Bank of <hi>England, That it extends its Credit at home beyond the real Fund.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>He confeſſeth at firſt, <hi>The Doctor hath propoſed that</hi> 400 l. <hi>is to cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culate</hi> 1000 l. In Page the 3d, ſays, <hi>He is ſo far from ſuppoſing that theſe Bills will be paid in ſpecie, that he makes no manner of Proviſion for it, and that the Bills aere to carry themſelves from the Bank and to the Bank, without any Circulation or Profit.</hi> In another place, page 4. he ſays, <hi>But if a Man ow'd</hi> 1500 l. <hi>he is excluded from all benefit of this Bank.</hi> And at laſt he concludes, <hi>That, it's needleſs here to object the want of Cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainty, that the Governours of this Bank ſhall not miſmanage in ſeveral particulars, which might require Parliamentary Proviſions:</hi> Not to men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion any more of his ſenſleſs ſtuff, about the <hi>Borrower</hi> and the <hi>Lender,</hi> any man that ever was at the Office to ſubſcribe, may preſently ſee that he is wholly ignorant of the <hi>Doctor</hi>'s Bank; and then let the World Judge what an impudent abuſive Fellow this muſt needs be, that will pretend to give ſo falſe an Account of a Bank that he does not underſtand, when it is ſo eaſie for him at any time to go to the Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice every other day in the week, and be rightly inform'd: But this is like one of <hi>Briſcoe</hi>'s Hirelings, ſet on purpoſe to exclaim againſt others, and commend only his National—Bank, which is the very worſt of all, and as yet no better than a What-d'-ye-call-'em Hodge-Podge-Bank, <hi>(compos'd more by the multitude of Hands, than the Wiſdom of Heads)</hi> which themſelves cannot tell what to make of, it is ſo much altered
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:51040:13"/>and diſguiſed from <hi>Briſcoe</hi>'s firſt Propoſal; and yet this ſeems to be the moſt practicable Scheme of all; Inſomuch that he cannot appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hend any Difficulty in ſettling Eſtates upon Truſtees, to be ſubject to its proportion of Loſs and Gain: Whereas if Eſtates muſt be ſettled, there ſhall never want large Accounts of Loſſes and Charges, as long as thoſe Eſtates are liable to make them all good.</p>
               <p>But at laſt it's very obſervable, that notwithſtanding this Author has ſo much praiſed <hi>Briſcoe</hi>'s Bank, yet at the ſame time he hath pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed another of his own, as much more excellent and preferrable of the two, which is juſt ſuch another Treacherous Trick as <hi>Briſcoe</hi> ſerv'd Dr. <hi>Chamberlen,</hi> firſt to write largely in Commendation of the <hi>Doctor</hi>'s, and contribute 150 <hi>l.</hi> to the carrying it on in <hi>Scotland;</hi> and then to dedicate another Senſeleſs one of his own to the King, and and offer it to the Parliament to paſs it into an Act.</p>
               <p>If this Author had ſhew'd himſelf a Man of Senſe, he ſhould have been anſwer'd in all particulars; but it's endleſs to reply to all the Nonſenſe that is offer'd in Print: And therefore I think this little Fisking Curr is not worth any Mans Notice.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="colophon">
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed and Sold by <hi>T. Sowle</hi> in <hi>White-Hart-Court</hi> in <hi>Grace-Church-Street,</hi> 1696.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:51040:13"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
